<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tessaradelphus, or The four brothers The qualities of whom are contayned in this old riddle. Foure bretheren were bred at once without flesh, bloud, or bones. One with a beard, but two had none, the fourth had but halfe one. Collected and translated, by Thomas Harrab.</title>
            <author>Harrab, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106009</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841734</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6336</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02664)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6336)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 961:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tessaradelphus, or The four brothers The qualities of whom are contayned in this old riddle. Foure bretheren were bred at once without flesh, bloud, or bones. One with a beard, but two had none, the fourth had but halfe one. Collected and translated, by Thomas Harrab.</title>
                  <author>Harrab, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Birchley Hall press?] permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Lancashire? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An attack on Lutheranism, Calvinism, Anabaptism, and Anglicanism.</note>
                  <note>Printer conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:1"/>
            <p>Teſſaradelphus, OR The foure Brothers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The qualities of whom are contayned in this old Riddle.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Foure bretheren were bred at once</l>
               <l>Without fleſh, bloud, or bones.</l>
               <l>One with a beard, but two had none,</l>
               <l>The fourth had but halfe one.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected and tranſlated.</hi> By THOMAS HARRAR.</p>
            <p>permiſſu ſuperiorum, 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>REader, I hauing trauailed in diuers parts of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world, chiefelie to take a diligent viewe of the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry sectes (which ſome call Relgions) vvhich are nowe in theſe parts thereof; and finding that to one obiecting their diſagreements one with another, they preſently anſwere: that they agree all in fundamentall pointes, although they diſſent in ſome matters, which they ſay, appertaine not to faith. Knowing by experience this anſwere to be moſt falſe, I thought it worth the labour to ſette before thine eyes very briefly, yet plainly, the foure Principall Sects, which are ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allowed, or permitted in ſome countries here in Europe; out of which, the multitude of petite Sects iſſue, to the end thou mayeſt ſee the irreconciliable differences amongſt them. And when thou haſt dilligently conſidered them, I hope thou wilt ſay of them, that <hi>recitaſſe eſt confutaſſe,</hi> the rehearſing of them is the confuting of them. They are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely comprehended in the Ridle aforeſaide, for they were all bredde with Martin Luther, although they came forth ſome of them after, as thou ſhalt ſee in this litle Treatiſe. I call them brothers, as they (partly forced by Catholikes, and partely to deceaue the ignorant) doe ſometimes ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, although in their writings they condemne one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the pit of Hell. Thou wouldeſt know who theſe foure be: Marry Lutheraniſine, Caluiniſme, Anabaptiſme, and Anglianiſme. Some wil perhaps ſay, that Religions or Sects ſhould rather be termed ſiſters, becauſe they are in the latine tongue of the feminine gender; but I anſwere, that Sects and Schiſmes taking their denomination of their Authours, who were men, may be well of the maſculine gender, I call the religion of England Anglianiſme, becauſe it among the reſt hath no one eſpeciall Authour, but is ſette forch by the Prince, and Parliament. The ſame Religion is now recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:6336:3"/>in Scotland, becauſe the King is one and the ſame of both Kingdomes, as alſo of Ireland, and other Iſles. Theſe foure brothers (as I terme them) are without fleſh, bloud, or bone, becauſe indeed there is no ſubſtance at all, or ſappe of religion, but certaine ſhadowes and ſhewes in them, as thou mayeſt ſee in the ſequell. One of them hath a beard, that is, ſome ſeemley face of a man; I meane ceremonies of Religion, as Lutheraniſme hath, and two, to wit, Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, and Anabaptiſme, no beardes at all, except here and there a fewling haire, that is, no ceremonies to accoumpt of, but ſome fewe remnants not worth the reckoning. Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme hath after a faſhion halfe a beard, for that it retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet ſome ceremonies of auncient Religion, although dayli decreaſing. In reading this litle booke, thou mayeſt take a view of them all, and conſider well with thy ſelfe, whether there be any hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in any of them, which are oppoſite to the vniuerſall Catholik Church, ſo renoumed ouer the world, for ſo many ages together.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell in Chriſt.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Martin Luther.</head>
            <p>MArtin Luther, the Author of this firſt Sect, was borne at Iſleb in the County of Mansfield, Anno 1483. the two and twentith day of October; his father was called Iohn Ludder, and his mothers name was Margaret, people of meane degree; ſome ſay that his mother conceaued him of an Incubus: but whether that be true or no, I wil not heere diſpute. Many write that the Deuil and he were very fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar one with another, and that they did eate a buſhel of ſalt together. And howe on a time, when the Goſpel was read at Maſſe, <hi>erat Ieſus eijciens demonium.</hi> Luther threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the ground, crying that is not I, that is not I: he chaunged his name from Ludder, which ſignifieth in their tongue Mocker, Theeſe, or Filth, into Luther, which beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth a pure man. So the Manichees chaunged their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters name Manes, that is, madde, into Manichee; which ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifieth to powre downe Manna. Lib. de here. c. 42.</p>
            <p>After that Luther had beſtowed his young yeares in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane letters, and had beene brought vp in the colledges of Magdeburge, and Senach in Turing, he gaue himſelfe to the ſtudie of ciuil Lawe, but preſently after, one of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions walking with him out of the towne, was ſtrocken ſtarke dead with a thunder-bolte, Luther not hurt, but all on a ſmoake; with this chaunce he was ſo frighted, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently he left the world, and put himſelfe into a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Auguſtin Friars in the towne of Erford, Anno. 1504. his companions wondren at this chaunge in him, hauing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene ſo much as one: ſparke of religion, or piety in him, but rather plaine ſignes of debanchements and diſorders. He had ſcarce ended his yeare of probation, but he grewe prowd, and haughty, hauing indeed ſome more learning then his fellowes, ouer whome he would dominiere and
<pb facs="tcp:6336:4"/>play the Maſter. For which cauſe as an vnruly fellow, he was ſent from thence to Wittenberge, to a Couent of the ſame order, Anno 1508. And at the ſame time there being a diuiſion betweene certaine howſes of that order, (for ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Monaſteries banded againſt their Generall) Luther took part with the reuolted, and was ſent to Rome as an aduocate of their cauſe. After this, Pope Leo the tenth hauing ſette forth Indulgences, for ſuch as would contribute to the wars againſt the Turks, the promulgation whereof was aſſigned to the Iacobin Faiars, and not to the Auſtenes, as they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; Stambitius Generall of the ſaid Auſtenes tooke it in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil parte, becauſe ſuch charge had beene accuſtomed to be committed to his Order, which was matter of no ſmal cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit: And for very ſpite ſette vp Luther, whome he knew to be fitte for ſeditious exployts, and tongued at will, as alſo bolde and venterous, to preach againſt the abuſe of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and Collectors of Indulgences. This Stambitius was emboldened ſo to doe, by the countenance of Fredericke Duke of Saxony, who was ſoare offended with the Pope, becauſe he had not the Biſhopricke of Magdeburge, but it was giuen to the Arche-Biſhoppe of Ments, who vnder the Pope had the aſſigning of the preaching of the Pardons. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then mounting into the pulpit, thundred againſt the Collectors, and Preachers of Pardons, more vehemently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede then Stambitius would haue had him to haue done, flouting, mocking, and ſcoffing at them, and now and then girding at the Pope himſelfe, inſomuch as it irked Stambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us that he had ſette him on worke; but now it was paſt his helpe: For many grew colde in deuotion towards this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, by reaſon of Luther his preaching againſt it, and ſent the Collectors backe not only empty handed, but loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo with contumelies, and reproaches. He growing more malapert for that the people gaue eare vnto him, was ſo audacious, as he wrote to the Arch-Biſhoppe of Ments, and to him of Brandeburg againſt the Collectors, who made no reckoning of him, nor of his letters. He ſette forth alſo
<pb facs="tcp:6336:4"/>certaine Theſes or propoſitions againſt the foreſaide, taxing Eccliaſticall perſons of negligence and ignorance. Tekell ſuperior of the Iacobins, ſet forth contrary propoſitions, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering his, and calleth Luther Heretike.</p>
            <p>At this time in very truth, there was great corruption in manners, and the Clergy was nothing ſo vigilant and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as aforetime; which thinges facilitated Luther his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. All the Chriſtian world was Catholike, and for many hundred yeares together, had no Heretical enemies to reckon of: Not any Proteſtant, or Puritane had euer beene heard of, which made Church-men to grow leffe watchfull, and to liue at their eaſe, wallowing in wealth and pleaſures. Pope Leo hearing of theſe tumults wrote to the Duke of Saxony, to ſend Luther to his Legat Caietan, who was with the Emperour Maximilian, or elſe to ſend him to Rome, where the cauſe might be heard; but the Duke excuſed the matter, and Luther wrote moſt humbly vnto the Pope, and offered to be ſilent hereafter, ſo that his aduerſaries would ſurceaſe. Neuertheleſſe, the matter grew worſe; for Silueſter Prierias a Iacobin, Maſter of the Popes pallace, buckled with Luther, and extolled the Popes authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Councels, and powers on the earth, in ſuch ſort, as Luther enraged with his aſſertions, abaſed the ſame more then euer. Diuers Iacobins tooke Silueſter his part, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Auguſtines defended Luther: And the broyles grewe ſo hoate, that at length Luther his complices, called in queſtion the power of the Pope about Indulgences, and queſtioned workes meritorious, and ſatisfactory, and ſundry other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not doubted of before; but Luther himſelfe would not ſeeme to doubt thereof, for in his firſt tome he auoucheth the ſame, affirming, that the Pope the immediate Vicar of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, hath authority to diſtrubute Indulgences.</p>
            <p>After all this, he humbled himſelfe againe to the Pope, and confeſſed his faultes and was ſent to Cardinall Caietan, before whome, he confeffed the Catholike faith; and with great proteſtations ſubmitted himſelfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:5"/>
            <p> He was yet once againe cited to Rome, but he appealed to the future general Councell, proteſting that he would not deminiſh the authority of the Pope, ſo that he be of a ſound opinion, for that was his clauſe. He wrote vnto the Pope alſo prayſing him, and diſprayſing his Legate and officers, and laid all faults on others. Many giddy-headed people at this time ranne headlong after Luther, ſtared on him, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, and encouraged him to higher matters. He writeth to the Emperour, to Knges, and to Princes, crying vpon them to reforme the Church, which phraſe of ſpeech pleaſed many, proteſting that he would change nothing, for he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as yet within his Couent, and ſaide Maſſe. The people applauded him on each ſide, which made him more proude and arrogant, inſomuch as he would ſay, turne thine eyes towardes me Germany, I am ſent to ſaue thee.</p>
            <p>The firſt Clergie-man that euer followed Luther, was Carolaſtade Archdeacon of Wittenberg: This man and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſputed with D. Eckius a Prebend of Ingolſtade, at Lipſe before Duke George, brother to Fredericke Duke of Saxony; and they both ſubmitted their opinions to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of Erfor and Paris, but ſtill reuolted againe. In this hoate conference, Luther burſt forth into theſe ſpeeches. This quarrell was not begunne for the honor of God, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it be ended by him. The Pope wrote againe to the Duke of Saxony, blaming him for protecting of Luther, but he ſent him a milde anſwere, ſaying that his holines his Nuncio was of opinion, that Luther ſhould not goe out of that coaſte, for feare of ſcattering of Hereſies elſe where. But indeed Luther had reſolued, if he had beene driuen out of Saxony, to retire himſelfe into Bohemia, yet feared he the Huſſites, becauſe he had affirmed them to be Heretikes. In fine, the Pope ſeing him ſo rebellious, and ſo turning in and out, excommunicated him by name, in <hi>Bulla Caena Domini.</hi> Who preſently when he heard of it growing deſperate, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited out all his poyſon, calling the Pope Ante-chriſt, and vnderſtanding that his bookes were burned as hereticall, he
<pb facs="tcp:6336:5"/>in a rage at Wittenberge burned the bookes of the common Law, with the Bull of Leo. He cried out to the people, let vs waſh our handes in the bloud of the Pope, of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and of al the Romiſh filth. So in the dſputation at Lipſe when he was admoniſhed to vſe modeſty in ſpeech, and writings; I will write (ſaid he) other kinde of ſtuffe, if I knew that it would diſpleaſe the Sea of Rome: Whilſt they triumph ouer ſome hereſie of mine, I will inuent new (ſaith he) in <hi>Praf. cap. Bab.</hi> He vſed ſtill in ſpeaking and writing, moſt filthy wordes and tearmes of ribaudry, and cauſed the Pope and Cardinals, to be pictured, and ſette forth in diuers places, in moſt filthy and vgly ſhapes. He reſolued forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to build a Religion of liberty, and to abandon Auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Celibates or ſingle liues, Faſtings, Chaſtities, and ſuch like, and to giue euery man leaue to beloeue what him liſt: And ſo it ſhould be moſt pleaſing to fleſh and bloud, and conſequently, be eaſilie receaued of many. To this end he wrote that it was lawful to beleeue what he would; that we were either predeſtinated, or reprobated, ſo as we could not doe withall: That euery Chriſtian was a prieſt, and might preach the word of God.</p>
            <p>The Emperor Charles came into Germany, before whom Luther was conuented, with letters of ſafe conduct (this was at Worms) where he behauing himſelfe heretically, yet with great diſſimulation, he was ſent backe, and condemned by the Emperor for an Heretike: he retired himſelf into a caſtle called Alſtat, belonging to the Duke of Saxony, yet with commandement, that he ſhould keep himſelfe ſecret, for feare of the Emperor. This he tearmed his Pathmos, here he wrote bookes ſarſed with all manner of contumelies, and oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious ſpeeches; he called the vniuerſity of Paris, which had condemned his doctrine, the vttermoſt hall of Ante-Chriſt, the back-dore of Hell. At this time at Wittenberge they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to aſſault the Maſſe, (for Luther was yet in Friars ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, and ſaid Maſſe ſtill and to breake downe Images, which Luther vnderſtanding, was very much offended with them.
<pb facs="tcp:6336:6"/>He did forbidde that eyther Ariſtotle, or Plato, ſhould be taught in their vniuerſities, or any thing but the Bible. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolaſtade and Melancton his followers, were now become the one a ploughman, the other a Baker, for that they would liue by the ſweat of their browes; but Luther called them backe, and rebuked Carolaſtade for breaking Images, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that no Image was forbidden in the Scriptures, but only of God: he tranſlated the Bible into the German tongue which was preſently burned in moſt places. There were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only in the new Teſtament, 1400 places corrupted and falſified, yet notwithſtanding, a Lutheran miniſter in Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberge, inſtituted a feaſtiuall day, and called it the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bible; being the firſt Lutheran feaſtiuall day that euer was. And for al this, Luther altered the ſaid Bible three times after, and changed many things of the firſt. Then did others leape out and make tranſlations of their owne, as Zwinglius, whoſe verſion was by Luther condemned, yet ſtill others made tranſlations, to the number of 67. verſions, one condemning anothers, and taking away, and putting in what them pleaſed; yea, they rent out of the Bible whole bookes, which made plainely againſt their opinioms.</p>
            <p>Carolaſtadius began to deny the reall preſence of Chriſt, in the holy Sacrament, but Luther oppoſed himſelfe againſt it, and reprehended him ſharply, which made Carolaſtade to leaue Wittenberge; but they two meeting in an Inne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, and Carolaſtade ſaying, that he durſt defend his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption by writing: Luther tooke to his purſe, and gaue him a florence of gould, to doe ſo if he durſt againſt him, which he tooke on that condition. So Luther bought the warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sacramentaries, whereof afterwardes, he had his handes full; he and Zwinglius brawled about the tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Bible, he renounced all generall Councels, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, and would not endure the word Clergy. He permitted men to change their wiues, would haue no viſible head of the Church; he would gladly haue denyed the reall preſence, but the words were ſo plaine he could not, as he.
<pb facs="tcp:6336:6"/>He cauſed Carolo ſtade to be baniſhed: whilſt Frederik Duke of Saxony he durſt not alter the Maſſe, but he pulled out of the litanies, the name of the holy Trinity. He with Melanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon would haue abandoned all liberal arts. He could neuer endure the Zwinglians, nor Sacramentaries, but tearmed them Apoſtles of the Diuel; Arians, Pelagians, &amp;c. He did al that he could in deſpite of the Councell of Trent, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted that he would oppoſe himſelfe, againſt the doctrine it ſhould ſet forth, bee what it will. He was both in doctrine and manners an enemy to good works, and taught that only faith was ſufficient, which doctrine brought ſorth fruits ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; as for example, one of his Diſciples a woman of Lipſe a widow, by her owne ſonne was gotten with childe, who when ſhee was great retired her ſelfe, and cauſed the child being a girle to be brought vp, her ſonne (the father) not knowing of it; when this girle was twelue years of age, the ſonne father of it, married the ſame girle, which by this meanes was his ſiſter, his daughter, and his wife; his mother knowing all. This ſinfull woman lying on her death-bedde, confeſſeth all to Luther, who with his ſchollers of Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge pronounced, that the quietnes of this marriage ought not to be troubled, and that they muſt permitte the woman without other puniſhment, to goe to heauen with only faith. He ſtirred vp the common people to rebellion, foa vvhich, many thonſands of them were ſlaine, and was the cauſe of the great warres of Germany, vvherin was moſt cruell car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and ſlaughter. He liked faire women ſo well, as that eſpying a beautifull damſell, in the Dutches of Saxony her trayne, he proteſted that if all the Diuels of hell were ſuch, he would gladly be amongſt them, which ſpeech the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe thought ſtrange, to proceed out of the mouth of him, who preofoſſed himſelfe to be the Reformer of the Chriſtian world, but the Duke anſwered, that Luther was fleſh and bloud as other men be: He made loue ſecretly to one Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine Bore, a Nunne, but durſt not marrie her as long as the Duke liued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:7"/>
            <p> Yet Carolaſtade firſt of all Prieſts married a woman, not ſecretly, but openly; and that with triumph. This wretched Prieſt (as he himſelfe ſaith) was ſo enraged with luſt, that he was like to loſe his ſences; and at his marriage, was Maſſe ſong after a new faſhion, and this collect was made and put in: God which after ſo long and wicked blindueſſe of thy Prieſts, haſt vouchſafed to giue ſuch grace to bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Carolaſtade, that he firſt of al not reſpecting the Popes lawe, durſt enterpriſe to marry a wife, graunt we beſeech thee, that all prieſts comming to their wittes, fallowing his ſteps, their concubines caſt out or married, may be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the fellowſhip of a lawfull bed, through the Lord &amp;c. Then followeth the proſe. God in thy power, Andrew Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolaſtade doth exult &amp; reioyce, coupled in mariage; diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuch like ſtuffe was thruſt into that Maſſe which I omit, and ended with this collect: Let the miſteries of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment receiued, O Lord, ſuccour vs, and as we reioyce in the connubial celebrity of Andrew Carolaſtade, ſo cauſe, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, that marriages of prieſts may happily beginne through the whole world, more happily goe forward, and moſt happily ende, through the Lord &amp;c. Many Fryars, Moncks and others followed this example of his, leaping out of the monaſteries and cloiſters, and got them wenches, and ſo became Goſpellers; ſome caſting their Habites got great breeches, and ſhort cloaks with ſwords by their ſides, and preached in that attire, ſome in one colour, ſome in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſome of one Sect, ſome of another; inſomuch as almoſt euery day, you might ſee a new religion coyned; but euerie one had his woman, or elſe no bargaine: Luther alſo, after the Duke was dead married his Nunne, and had by her three ſonnes.</p>
            <p>Many more thinges are recorded of this man, which are eaſily ſeene in diuers writers: Theſe may ſuffice to giue the vnlearned Reader a taſte of this Reformer; and now you ſhal ſee what he leſt to his followers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Lutheraniſme.</head>
            <p>FIrſt then, the Churches of the Lutherans ſtand ſtill as they did in the olde time, and the Cloiſters for the moſt part in vvoods, and in deſart places, as thoſe of the order of S.Bennet, and of S.Bernard nothing defaced, (except Images is ſome places, vvhere Carolaſtadius came) in ſuch ſort as a Catholike entring into the Lutheran Temples, vvill deeme that he is in Catholik churches. For there ſhal he ſee the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſeparated from the body of the Church, but yet not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the ſame vvhich vvas before. There is the great Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar ſtill ſtanding, the Crucifixe aboue the Images of the twelue Apoſtles, diuers Chappels and places of prayer, the font for Baptiſme, in many churches are the Organs, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and other ornaments of the Catholike Church; all in outward ſhewe haue the markes of the auncient Religion of their forefathers: In croſſe high wayes the Crucifixe is to be ſeene as in Catholike time, which the Lutherans reuerence.</p>
            <p>The people paſſing by litle Churches in the country, enter into them, to ſay their prayers before the Aſtar, they keepe their Chappels neate and fine, in good reparation, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enter into their Temples (for ſo they tearme them, and not Churches) but they kneele downe, turning their faces towards the great Altar, they keep the ſhadowes of Biſhops and Prieſts, yet haue they chaunged the names of them, in ſteed of Biſhop, is the name Superintendent. This hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him diuers pariſhes, and euery pariſh hath his Curate, whom they call in the Germaine tongue Pfather, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons in their language called Helffers: The Superintendent hath eyther ſome reuennewes, or elſe is maintained by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like contribution.</p>
            <p>But to know the diuers faſhions of Lutherans, it is firſt to be vnderſtoode, that Luthers Sect is deuided into two principal Factions: The one is called the Confeſſion of Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge
<pb facs="tcp:6336:8"/>made by Melancthon, Anno 1530, and preſented to the Emperour: The other is the Interim, which was a proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made, Anno 1584. vntil the Councell had determined matters of Religion, which Interim after tooke force, and was reciued in Soxony, and in diuers Emperiall townes, as in Hamburge, Lubecke, Luneburg, Magdeburg, Hall, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberge, in the Marquiſate of Brandeburg, and in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. The book of this Interim in the German tongue is called Rijrchenordming, that is, the ordinance of the Church, wherein are written the formes and ceremonies of their Maſſes, made of an newe faſhion, yet retaining many things of antiquity, as <hi>Kyrie eleiſon, Alleluia,</hi> and <hi>Dominus vobiſcum.</hi> The Pfather comming neere the Altar, ſaith <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteor,</hi> with other prayers as the Catholike prieſt doth, and conſecrateth, and communicateth as he doth, but mingleth withal diuers prayers in the vulgar tongue, and alſo reciteth the goſpell in the ſame. They doe not eleuate, for that they think the body of Chriſt to be preſent there to be eaten, and not to be adored but only of the receauer; yet many of that Sect hold it as a thing indifferent, whether it be eleuated or no, and ſo was it left in a Sinode by the Lutherans of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark in Norway, 1537. and in another, 1549. and allowed by Pomeran and Camerarius. The Lutheran prieſt when he ſaith Maſſe is veſted with a Surpleſſe, and with a Coape or Veſtment, and hath two Deacons aſſiſting him, the one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the epiſtle, the other the goſpel; in ſome places in latin, and in others in the vulgar tongue: comming to the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, and to other ceremonies, he reciteth in his language the ſame wordes that the Catholike prieſt doth, he holdeth the Hoaſt, and the Chalice as he doth, the Altar is prepared, and Tapers burning vpon it, as amongſt Catholikes: Their Chalices are all of maſſiue gould, and that great ones yea in country Churches. The Pfather ending his collects, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth towards the people &amp; bleſſeth them, making the ſigne of the Croſſe, vnto which all bow themſelues kneeling.</p>
            <p>They ſay but one Maſſe in one Church on a day, thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:6336:8"/>who wil receiue come neere to the Altar, and kneele as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks doe, the prieſt ſo veſted turneth giueth benediction, and putteth the Hoaſt into the receiuers mouth, as it is to be ſeene in Saxony, and elſe where: Then the Deacon giueth the Chalice vvith vvine conſecrated. They neuer ſay Maſſe but ſome communicate, for Luther abandoned all priuate Maſſes, ſo he tearmed them. They ſay their euenſong in the latine tongue, anſwering one another, after the manner of Catholikes: Thus much of the Lutheran Interimiſts.</p>
            <p>They which follow the Confeſſion of Anſburg, haue not their Moſſe as the Interimiſts haue: Their Temples are in the ſame manner as the others, their Pfather or Helffer, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth into the pulpit with his Surpleſſe, and there preacheth, hauing done he goeth downe, &amp; before the Altar he ſaith di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers prayers alone, after, turning towardes the people, he prayeth with a loud voice, and ſo ſaith a kinde of Maſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not with ſuch ceremonies and ornaments, as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terimiſts vſe, for he hath neyther Coape nor Veſtment, and he readeth the epiſtle and goſpel himſelfe. Hauing ended the collects, he rehearſeth the inſtitution of the Supper, in the vulgartongue, and conſecreteth the Hoaſts; they who vvill communicate come before the Altar, the Superintendent or pfather, taketh the paten of gould in his hands, on which are the little Hoaſts conſecrated, and making the ſigne of the Croſſe, putteth them into the receiuers mouths, vvith ſuch words as the Catholikes doe. After him followeth the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con with the Chalice, and giueth to euery one ſaying take, drink, this is the true bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, wich was ſhed for thee. They who receane, pray before and after by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as Catholiks doe: the actions and benedictions being ended, euery one goeth his way. When ſolemne feaſts draw nigh, the Preachers exhort the people to confeſſe, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, ſo Luther ordained. Vpon the euen of the feaſtiuall day the Churches are open, and the Superintendent, and the Helffers, are neere the Altars where they heare Confeſſions: Thoſe who come to confeſſe drawe neere, and ſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb facs="tcp:6336:9"/>doe ſpeake to the Helffer: If they deſire to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, three or foure come at once: If any haue his conſcience burdened, he confeſſeth ſecretly, demaundeth pardon of God, and receiueth abſolution. In many places they kneele, and none are married, but ſuch as goe to confeſſion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament: When one is ſicke, he ſendeth for the Pfather, who goeth with an Hoaſt not conſecrated, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth all to goe out of the ſicke man his chamber, and then exhorreth him to diſcharge his conſcience by confeſſion, which done, he giueth him abſolution, making the ſigne of the Croſſe vpon his head, then there is a napkin ſpread vpon a table, on which he fetteth the Chalice, and Paten, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rehearſed the wordes of the inſtitution, he conſecrateth the bread and wine: After the confeſſion of the ſicke man, the people come in againe and kneele all there, and then the Pfather taketh the Hoaſt, with the conſecrated Chalice, and giueth them to the ſicke man, as he doth in the Church,</p>
            <p>Yet doe not all keepe their ordinances ſo ſtrictly, as they are ſet downe, by reaſon that euery man may belecue what he will: For one ſaid in giuing the Sacrament, drinke, and cate, and doe not forget thy God: ſome others wil ſay, take cate, and remember the Lord: other ſay only a Pater noſter: another hauing forgotten his Chalice, and not finding a glaſſe, tooke a pottage diſh out of the kitchin, powred the wine into it, and giuing it to the ſicke man, ſaid, take and drinke this diſh of the new Teſtament in forgiuenes of ſins. They neuer reſerue conſecrated Hoaſts, for Luther taught directly againſt all antiquity, that out of the Communion, Chriſts body was not there.</p>
            <p>In ſome places they ſay their euenſong as the Interimiſts doe, they ſing them euery ſaterday, and haue the Organs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, as the Catholikes haue, and ſinging boyes which ſing pſalmes, and notes. The bels found at the dawning of the day, at noone, and at night, as among Catholikes. Yet is there difference amongſt them in diuers places, for ſome doe theſe aforeſaid thinges in one manner, ſome in another.
<pb facs="tcp:6336:9"/>In the Marqueſſe of Brandebutge his Chappell, after euerie pſalme, in liewe of <hi>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</hi> (which Luther put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) they diſcharged their piſtols, which made an hideous noiſe with fire and ſmoake. Both the Interimiſts, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſioniſts ſolemnize feaſtes, they highlie eſteeme Maundie thurſday, on which day they confeſſe and receiue, and doe celebrate with religious reuerence good friday. Aboue all, they keepe holy the feaſts of the bleſſed virgin Mary, of the Apoſtles and Martirs, as Catholikes doe: And no other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is ſeene, but that the Catholikes obſerue the Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Calendar, and they the olde vſe; yet confeſſing that the reformation is right. This is to be ſeene in Ausburg, Spires, Wormes, Franckforte, Ratisbone, and in other places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any contention at all. They bring their children to the Fonts to be chriſtened, which were In ancient time, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the P father hath recited the inſtitution of Baptiſme, he abſolueth the infant from originall ſinne, coniureth the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to leaue this newe Chriſtian which he baptiſeth, making three times the ſigne of the Croſſe; and other thinges after the Catholike faſhion. They obſerue alſo the Catholike ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in Marriage, for the moſt part they abſtaine from fleſh on Fridayes, Saterdayes, and in Lent, their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes are eſteemed holy, and when one is dead, there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſingers with boyes kept for that purpoſe, which goe before the Corps, and ſing pſalmes in the vulgar tongue all the vvay, and in the Church: Manie of them beleeue that there is Purgatòry, and doe pray for the dead: The Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perſons in Emperiall Citties enjoy their reuenues, and ſo doe the Religious alſo.</p>
            <p>But the Religious, which are in Lutherane Dutchies and Countries haue beene baniſhed, and poore children are put in their places, and brought vp in learning: Eccleſiaſticall perſons amongſt them, differ in habit from the Laytie: The Confeſſioniſts are in many Emperial townes, as in Ausburg, Vlmes Dingnelſpil, Bibrace, Norlingen Hedpron, in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, Strausburg, Haganan, Wiſemburge, Landan, Spires,
<pb facs="tcp:6336:10"/>Wormes, Oppenheny, and Franckeforte. There be diuers Princes, as the Duke of Wittenberg, the Lantgraue of Heſſe, the Marqueſſe of Brandeburg, and other Counts and Lords which follow the Confeſſion of Ausburge, with an oath to admit no other Religion in their Territories.</p>
            <p>When all the Country was in an vproare about theſe new Sects, many Sectaries met together at Spires, and although they were of different opinions, yet joyned they in league a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholike Church, and againſt the Emperor, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting that they vvould dye in their opinions; And of this proteſtation they were tearmed Proteſtans; but this league was afterwards more eſtabliſhed at Smalcade.</p>
            <p>See here many auncient ceremonies yet amongſt the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, which make vp a juſt beard in the face of the eldeſt brother Lutheraniſme: Now to Iohn Caluin.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What manner of man Iohn Caluin was.</head>
            <p>HE was borne at Noyon in Picardy in Fraunce the tenth of Iuly, Anno 1509. His name indeed was Iohn Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſonne of Gerard Chaunie, and of Iane France: But as Luther chaunged his name, ſo did he, and called himſelfe Caluin; and becauſe the Anagramme of his name maketh Lucian, he vvould be called Alcuin, vvho vvas the learned maſter of Charles the great. After his infancy, in ſome forte beſtowed in learning ſitte for that age, he was ſent to Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and after that to Bourges, to ſtudy the ciuill Law; and there meeting with one Melchior Wolmer a Germane, the greeke Reader, was by him drawne to the ſtudy of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for that he eſpied a ready wit in him; and Melchior him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was ſectetly a Lutheran, but outwardly ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Catholike: He opened vnto Caluin the ſecrets of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Sect. After ſome time ſpent with Wolmer, of whom he learned Luther his Religion, and ſome skill in the Greek tongue, he left the Vniuerſitie, and returned to Noyon,
<pb facs="tcp:6336:10"/>where his father had prouided for him a Prebend, &amp; a Cure in the country: Yet Wolmer ſolicited him ſtill by letters to become a Lutheran, yea, after that hee vvas returned into Germany. But he went from Noyon to Paris, where he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan ſecretly to teach his owne opinions, and being ſuſpected he went to Angoleſme, where he was maintayned for the ſpace of three years, by one Tillet curat of Claixe, &amp; Canon of Angoleſme, to whom he did read greeke: And there it was ſaid, and diuers haue written it, that he was accuſed &amp; conuicted of a moſt filthy crime. Here he beganne to frame his Inſtitutions, and did read the ſame to diuers ſecretlie where he durſt; he was abſtinent and of a ſharp wit: but he abſtayned (as himſelfe confeſſed) not for cauſe of Religion, but becauſe his ſtomacke was weake, and he was ſubiect to the Megreame. He would not as Luther his cuſtome was to doe, vomitte out all that he thought, but kept ſtill ſome things to himſelfe, outwardly ſhewing himſelfe otherwiſe then he was within; his words were few, and he giuen to be ſolitary, for naturally he was Melancholike, opening him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to few, and not delighting in company, and euer had in his mouth, <hi>Nunquam minus ſolus, quam cum ſolus:</hi> That he was neuer leſſe alone, then vvhen he vvas alone. At Ango<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſme in Tillet, his Gallery were ſome 3000. books and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts, which Caluin ſtill turned ouer in ſuch retired ſort, as his chiefeſt friends could hardly come to the ſpeach of him. Luther was cloquent and had a great gift in ſpeaking, and preaching; but Caluin contrary was very ſilly in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, &amp; had neither grace nor action in the pulpit, ſo asneuer any auditor was moued, but only by the name of Caluin: he in his ſpeech ſo vnpleaſing, and redious with his <hi>quidmoror</hi> cómon in his mouth. He was more skilfull in latin then Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was. he would often ſay, that Luther had done nothing vvorth a button, and that Chriſtendome vvas no more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to him, then a poore trauailer is obliged to one that ſheweth him his way a farre of; that it was to no purpoſe to follow his ſteppes, which was (ſaid he) to be halfe a Papiſt;
<pb facs="tcp:6336:11"/>but better it wer to build the Church altogether new: for he ſcorned to be any mans Diſctple. Diſpite and deſperation, made Luther an Arch-Sectary; and the deſire of glory and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation, made Caluin another author of vvorſe Hereſies: for this he writeth of himſelf. All who deſired pure doctrine came to me to learne, although I my ſelfe had but new be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, <hi>Prafat, in Pſal</hi> He called himſelfe a Ptophet, and ſpake and wrote in his owne praiſe, and vvas very eloquent in his mother tongue, vvhich cauſed many vnlearned to reade his bookes with delight. He vſed moſt diſpitefull, and reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vvordes againſt Kings, and Princes, calling them brute beaſts, fooles, and aſſes. If they band againſt God (that is to ſay, againſt his ſect) ſaith hee, wee ought rather to ſpit in their faces, then to obey them, in 6. Daniell, hee would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no man, except he ſubmitted himſelfe to him. Wolmar, vvho firſt founded the diſpoſition of his wit, vvriteth thus of him, to Farell his aſſociate, in the conqueſt of Geneua: I feare not ſo much (ſaith he) the ouer-thwartneſſe of his vvit, for this vice is ſit to aduance our affaires, to make him a ſtout defender of our opinions, for he vvil not ſo eaſily be catched but that he vvill be able to entrap our aduerſaries. This let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, cauſed great ſtirre betwixt him, and one Chriſtian, a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Poytiers, vvho ſcattered copies of it, by reaſon of the emulation vvhich was between him and Caluin: Whilſt he ſtayed in Angoleſme, he ſayned himſelfe to bee a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and ſaid, in conference with his companions, that what he ſaid, he did it but by way of diſputation, to finde out the truth. He paſſed from thence into Germany, and tooke Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua in his way, and ſaw many which were reuolted, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them Bucer, vvho brought him to Eraſmus Rotero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus (who then did but cry ayme) and the ſame Eraſmus, hauing ſounded Caluin, ſaid to Bucer, pointing at him: I ſee a great plague ſpring in the Church. Caluin returneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into France to Poytiers, where he got ſome diſciples, and he told them, that indeed Luther had found out but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſparke of light, vvhich gaue a little ayme a-farre off, to
<pb facs="tcp:6336:11"/>thoſe who trauayled in the dead time of the night, to giue them ſome ſmall glimmering of their iourney. But to come to light indeede, the Maſſe muſt be altogether aboliſhed, and the ſupper put in place thereof, where Chriſt (ſaid hee, to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the Lutheranes, and the Zwinglians) is really, but eaten ſpiritually, and by faith only; that the communion of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall fleſh, might enter into the ſoule by the irradiation of the holy Ghoſt. But diuers of his diſciples oppugned this aſſertion, and inuented new. When he had ſome few diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, he ſent them abroad with new names; for one that was Reader in a Hall of the Inſtitutes of law, they called Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur le Miniſter. And although the name (Miniſter) be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall name for Seruiteurs in the Church, and in the cómon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, yet Caluin firſt appropriated it to the Paſtors and Teachers of his new Church; and yet before it was neuer proper to any order or kinde of men of religion. Another was called the Gatherer: afterward, when their number in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, they ordayned Miniſters, Carders of wooll, Fullers, Drapers, Embroderers, and other artificers; which ſecretly preached; there was hardly to be found amongſt them, no not in the yeare 1540 any learned man. He rayſed great ſtirs at Geneua, but after many tumults hee became their chieſe Paſtor, where he changed all, and iudging criminall cauſes. He marryed the Widdow of Iohn Eſtordeur borne in Liege, in religion an Anabaptiſt, which left that ſect and became of Caluins religion; ſhee was called Idelette de Bure, a name not much differing from Luthers name: He neuer had child by her, although ſhee were yong and beautifull, he married his brother Anthony Caluin, to the daughter of Nicholas de Fer, who at Antwerp had played ſuch prancks, as hee vvas glad to runne away, and to ſhrowde himſelfe at Geneua (vvhich town was then become the receptacle of bankrupts, vvhore-mongers, murderers, and of all debauched people vvhich flocked thither out of diuers countries, and became of Caluins religion,) Hee made his brother a booke-ſeller, that he might diſperſe his bookes. But his daughter being
<pb facs="tcp:6336:12"/>taken in adultery, and deliuered to the Bonreau to be whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and catted, ſhamed her vncle Iohn ſo, that he could ſcarce looke vp or behould the people, to whome he deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this new goſpell. He ſent ſome few of his diſciples into America, to preach his goſpel there, becauſe he would ſeeme to be as zealous in planting, as the Catholiks were known to be: But by that time they came there, their prouiſion of wine wasall ſpent, and not knowing how to miniſter their communion for want of wine, they ſent to their maſter Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin to know his opinion, vvho anſwered, that being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by neceſſity, they might vſe in ſtead of wine, any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of drink, vſed in that part of the world: Beza was of the ſame opinion, and ſo vvas Luther vvho taught alſo, that for want of water, they might baptize in Ale, Beere, or Milke. Thus he taught what him beſt pleaſed, and his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to his followers was an Oracle: he liued and dominie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much at Geneua, where he ended his life moſt miſerably, being eaten with vermin to death, as hiſtories doe record.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> What religion Caluin left to his followers.</head>
            <p>HE allowed of no Image at all for Religious vſe, turning away the word Idol in the Bible, into the word Image, yet did he reſerue the picture of the Diuell. He allowed of no feaſt day, but the ſeauenth day, vvhich they tearme the Saboath; his church indeed was a long time without ſorme, or faſhion, for euery one vſed his owne manner, ſome in one fort and ſome in another; yet they al tearmed themſelues the faithfull children of Chriſt. They cannot endure the ſigne of the Croſſe, nor Altars, nor any honor to the name of Ieſus, nor faſting daies, nor chalices, but in their communion they vſe glaſſes. They will haue no head of their Church, but in ſteed of Biſhoppes and Prieſts, they haue them whome they tearme a name, not known in that ſence to antiquity: Their eccleſiaſticall officers are deuided into Miniſters, Auncients,
<pb facs="tcp:6336:12"/>or Watchmen and Deacons. In the ordinances of Geneua, there was a fourth kinde, to wit Doctors, but that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but a ſmal ſpace: Their Miniſters dot preach, adminiſter their Sacraments, and haue ſoueraigne authority. When one will bea Miniſter, he is propoſed to the Conſiſtory, in the preſence of the Miniſter, and Auncients, (theſe be ignorant artizans) afterward he is admitted to triall, where a chapter is aſſigned him to diſcourſe vpon, in the vulgar tongue; he muſt in no caſe alleadge any thing in latin in ſermons: But one chiefe point is, that he be well able to raile againſt the Pope and Catholike religion, as one of them began his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in this manner. The great locke-maſter (meaning the Pope) brought vp and fedde fat in the ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hin of Sathan &amp;c. which the audience applauding the preacher for his conceirs was much commended. The miniſter to be after trial in this ſort, is by the Preſident of the aſſembly (hauing taken ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) called in, who telleth him his faults and wants, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo commendeth ſomething in him: Then he giueth him his hand of aſſociation, and others doe the like making ſignes of amity, and ciuility; and this is all their making of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Yet before he be a receaued Miniſter, ſome church or congregation muſt make meanes to haue him, and thither he goeth, and if the people like of him, three or foure Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters aſſemble, and receaue him into the Miniſtery, and for their brother and companion, after that he hath ſubſcribed to the confeſſion of their faith, his auditors maintayne him, but his penſion thirty pounds, or forty pounds a yeare at the moſt, if he be vnmarried, if married, he may haue two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred crownes penſion: ſome would haue had them to ſerue without any wages at all, as the Anabaptiſts doe.</p>
            <p>If he which is called to the Miniſtery hath bin a Monke, Friar, Prieſt, or ſuch like, he muſt attend a while, vntill he haue diſgorged his Monkery (as they tearme it:) They are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies jelous of ſuch perſons; firſt they diſgrade them, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monke them, and then cal them to the Miniſtery. In diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them they vſe this ceremony, the party putteth off his
<pb facs="tcp:6336:13"/>habit, curſing him who veſted him therewith, then treadeth he it vuder his feete or renteth it: ſome of them dye their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit to make coates for their woemen, or children.</p>
            <p>If he be not married before, he taketh a woman, and then they account him their owne ſure; for you ſeldome or neuer ſhall finde any ſuch, which lefte not his calling by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fleſh, and not induced by the ſpirit: If any one would liue a ſingle life, they cry our preſently with Luther, that ſuch are not exempt from badde. Thus much for their Miniſtery; yet he who is a Lord of Fee, if he think him ſelfe able and ſufficient, without any more adoe, may goe vp into the pulpit, and teach ſubiects-</p>
            <p>They now and then leaue the Midiſtery, and become Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates, Phiſitions, and School emaſters; for they haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſions of chaunges, as want of maintenance, the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors liking another better then their owne, with many ſuch like: By the ordinances of Geneua, no Miniſter which hath beene a Religious man, can be Preſident in their Nationall Sinodes.</p>
            <p>The Auncients watch and marke if any of theirs commit any ſcandall, eſpecially if they goe to Maſſe, or to the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites: and they report the ſame to the Conſiſtory. The Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients and Ouerſeers are much like, yet there is ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, for the Ouerſeers are Aſſiſtants or Councellors to the Miniſters, and much inferior to them; they are indeed, as it were Beadles: The Ancients may depoſe the Miniſters, or ſilence them, vntill the next Colloque, or Sinode.</p>
            <p>The Deacons keepe the purſe for the poore, they gather the Miniſters penſion, viſite the ſicke, make Collections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, to defray common charges of warte, or of other affaires: They allure ſuch as can beare Armes, &amp; bring their names to the Conſiſtory. Theſe Deacons ſerue al turns, they be Porters, Readers, Seruants to the Conſiſtory, Aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to the Miniſters in the Supper, and diſtribute the glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: their Chaunters beginne their pſalmes, Aduertiſers, as Apparitors who ſummon the accuſed to appeare.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:13"/>
            <p> The Miniſters, Ancients, &amp; Ouerſeers, holde Colloques, which are voluntary aſſemblies of Miniſters, three or foure times a yeare, &amp; euery Miniſter hath his Ancient, where they diſpute of doctrine, and appeaſe diſorders, and take notice of memorable matters to be related to the Sinode; for the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node determinethal, being diuided into Prouincial, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, for generall they can haue none: For Lutheraniſme hath no participation with them; neither in Faith, Religion, nor Ceremonies, no more hath Anabaptiſme, nor Anglia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſme. In the Prouinciall Sinodes vvhich are kept yearely, they chooſe one whom they call a Moderator, and he is Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Sinode.</p>
            <p>The natural Sinode, is euery ſecond or third yeare, where euery Prouince hath his Miniſter, and Deputy: that is their higheſt Court.</p>
            <p>Their Conſiſtory is compoſed of al ſortes of perſons, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Cittizens, Courtiers, Artizans, and of the baſeſt ſorte of people, which many found fault with; but Caluin would haue it ſo. In theſe aſſemblies, ſeauen at the leaſt muſt judge caſes concerning the ſoule, for they may excommunicate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Sect, be he Kinge or Kezar, banniſh him out of their aſſemblies, and depriue him of Sacraments.</p>
            <p>This Conſiſtory, is kept in the Miniſters howſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideth, or in their Temple.</p>
            <p>The Auncients prye into the actions of their neighbours, and informe againſt them, and then the Aduertiſer is ſent to ſummon the accuſed: If he appeare not, he is called by the Miniſter to the ſermon, and after three times warning, is cut off from their Supper. If he appeare, he is brought into the Conſiſtory, where he ſtandeth bare-headed, and is forced to aske pardon, ſometimes there, &amp; ſometimes publikely at the ſermon, where his fault before vnknown, is made publike. If any haue daunced, they are greately puniſhed for it, and for curling their haire, and for ſuch like: If it be a perſonage of high degree, they conceale the crime, but declare publikely, that ſuch a perſon hath made ſatisfaction for his faulte. But
<pb facs="tcp:6336:14"/>by this meanes many offendors knowne to fewe, come to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen reproache, and many loſe their good name, which they had before. In very deed thoſe Conſiſtories and Sinodes are plaine inſtruments and trumpets of warre; for they wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund Kings and Princes: And to this end, Beza wrote to the Miniſters in Fraunce, that they ſhould not receaue into their Citties, Captaynes and officers in warre, but ſuch as were choſen and approued by their Conſiſtories and Sinods.</p>
            <p>They haue ruinated Churches where they could preuaile, and beaten them downe to the ground, and they exerciſe their Sect in vaſte places of townes, in barnes without any decking or hanging at all; for they abhorre the Churches of Chriſtians, and wil doe no exerciſe of Religion in them, but downe they muſt, if it lieth in their power: In other places, they make ſtables for horſes, or ware-howſes for Merchants of goodly Churches. In their new Temples they haue ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as in Colledges, for people to ſit on: There they mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſalute one another, eſpecially the delicate dames, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reuerence there is none to be done, neyther to God, to Angel, nor to Saint; no body knecleth, for then they cry out a Papiſt: Whileſt there they expect the Miniſters comming, ſome Brother or Cobler mounteth vp in his artizans araye, and readeth to them a chapter of the Bible, or an homely of Iohn Caluin.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter commeth in a gown ſometimes black, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of other colour, ſometimes in his cloake, with a hat of the common faſhion. The Miniſter or Preacher to the ſiſter of Henry the fourth King of France and Nauarre, neuer came to her, but with his ſword by his ſide, &amp; in a blew or violet cloake, with dublet and breeches of yellow chamlet, &amp; one of them preached in a garden, and made his pulpit the pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell of his ſworde ſticking in the ground, ſometimes they preached booted and ſpurred: And all this after, they haue had liberty of conſcience, for otherwiſe it might be excuſed; Yea. Anno 1599. the Miniſter of Cottendiere preached in a ſute of ginger colour, with his ſword and dagger at his ſide.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6336:14"/>
            <p> The Miniſter mounted into his chaire, maketh his prayer for all, they ſome ſtanding, ſome ſitting, here and there ſome kneeling, or as they pleaſe: the prayer is very ſhort, ſome twenty lines.</p>
            <p>Then he preacheth a ſermon of ſome pſalme in the vulgar tongue, with a lowde voice, al the people follow, men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, children, and ſeruants, ſome high, ſome lowe, ſome in tune, ſome out of tune, with great confuſion, without order or harmony. Then falleth he to his ſermon, which being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he prayeth againe very briefely, and then they ſing the ſection of the pſalme out to the end. You ſhal neuer ſee any among them, lift vp their hands or eies to ward Heauen, not neuer knocke their breaſte, nor ſigh; the moſt part among them will neuer kneele: In briefe, there ſhalt thou ſee no more deuotion, then is at a ſtage-play.</p>
            <p>They haue two Sacraments, Baptiſme, and the Supper. They baptize not by the ordinance of Geneua, but at the preaching ſo amongſt them: If they dye without baptiſme, they are ſaued. At baptiſme, ſome infants are holden in the armes of their godmothers, ſome lie in their cradles, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Miniſter hath rehearſed certaine words, he throweth a litle water vpon the childes face, and ſaith, I baptize thee &amp;c. As for godfathers, or godmothers, they litle regarde them: and they admit father and mother in ſteade of them. They giue them newe names, but no names of Idolators (as they tearme them) but rather names of Iewes, and of ſuch as were neuer Catholikes, but not the names of Saints.</p>
            <p>Their Supper they celebrate foure times in the yeare, they goe to it as to a ſermon, without any preparation; the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hauing ended his preaching, commeth downe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth himſelfe before the table, couered vvith a napkin; vppon the table, there is a baſon full of common bread, cut in peeces, and botles and glaſſes ſtanding: The Miniſter ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a peece of bread and giveth another to the chiefe of the Conſiſtory, ſome ſaying one ſort of words, and ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The common people kiſſe the Miniſter his hand in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing
<pb facs="tcp:6336:15"/>bread of him, but if they are perſons of account, the Miniſter kiſſeth the bread before he giue it to them. The Deacon giueth drink in a glaſſe to the Miniſter, after, others drink: They kneele not at all, but cate it either ſtanding or walking; they neuer goe to the ſicke with it, nor celebrate it, but in the aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>Marriage amongſt them is no Sacrament: They who are to be married, preſent themſelues at the preaching, and there without ring, prayer, benediction, or any ceremony at all, they are eſpowſed: No degrees are excepted, but brother, ſiſter, father, mother, diuerſity of religion, and fornication, with them diſſolueth the bond of marriage. If a Monke or a Friar apoſtate marrie a woman, and after leauing her, returne to his Monaſtery againe, ſhee by the authority of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may marrie another. If a man marrie a woman, and ſhee proue with childe by another man, he may forſake her, and marry another.: If a woman will ſweare that ſhee ſawe not her husband for the ſpace of a yeare, nor knoweth not where he is, ſhee may marry another.</p>
            <p>There is nothing that hath drawne multitudes to be of therir Sects ſo much, as the ſinging of their pſalmes, in ſuch variable and delightfull tunes: There the ſouldier ſingeth in warre, the artizans at their worke, wenches ſpinning, and ſewing, apprentiſes in their ſhoppes, and wayfaring men in their trauaile, litle knowing (God wotte) what a ſerpent ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hidden vnder theſe ſweete-flowers, vvhat venome is in this pleaſant liquor, and vvhat diſtraction is in this Sirens ſonge: this craft and ſbutilty did olde Heretikes vſe. Theſe diuine pſalmes are by them tranſported out of the Church, into the dwelling howſe, out of the Quire into the ſhoppe, and as abſurd it is for a ſhoomaker ſowing his ſhooe, to ſing one of theſe pſalms, as it is to ſing <hi>Miſereremei.</hi> or <hi>Depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundis.</hi> in his petitions to God Almightie.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rithmes or Rimes in the vulgar, are rather Bezaes ballads, and Marots muſes, then pſalmes of Dauid; for they vagary and goe out at their pleaſute, from faithfull tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:6336:15"/>and from the ſence of the holy Ghoſt, to make vp their Rime: For it was hard, yea impoſſible, to fall right vpon the feete of the Hebraicall poeſie, being full of allegories and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures. They ſeing this abſurdity confuted in an aſſembly at Mountpeliere, put the pſalmes into proſe, and ſo to ſtoppe the mouth of Papiſts, by ſinging them in the olde tune, and to leaue of Bezaes and Marots Rimes; but for feare of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning their former inuention, they left the matter vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided. Marot in the very firſt pſalme, inueraeth the ſence of the Prophet: Their Rimes indeed, are rather Paraphraſes of their owne braine, than the text of Scripture, and ſo are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the ballads of Beza, and of Marot. As for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot he was a wanton Courtier, a Poet, and a Muſition, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnlearned but in the mother tongue; a man in regard of his ignorance and loſe life, moſt vnfit to medle in ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine matters, or affaires. At the firſt they were taken but for ballads, and diuers ſung them to what tune they liked beſt, ſome in hunting and hauking, ſome in other exerciſes, but they were not ſung at ſermons: In the end Marot fledde to Geneua, and there made vp ſome fifty pſalmicall ballads: But continuing his loſe life, and it being known that he had debaunched his hoſteſſe, for the which he was openly whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, he fled from thence into Pyemont &amp; there he died; after whoſe death Beza made vp the reſt of the Pſalmical ballads, and Caluin cauſed muſitions to put ditties and tunes vnto them, wanton, light, and whatſocuer was delightful. In the yeare 1553, they ordayned that they ſhould be ſung in their Aſſemblles by ſections: This ſinging of ballads, is the only principall office, and ordinary exerciſe of their Religion; and what had they before.</p>
            <p>When any one dyeth he is put in a ſheet, and without ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony pompe, or prayer, he is carried by twoo poore fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes vnto the fieldes, or ditch, which the magiſtrate hath appointed for that purpoſe: There muſt be no weeping, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, nor ſadnes at all, nor ſigne of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>The miniſter goeth not with the corps, nor hath any thing
<pb facs="tcp:6336:16"/>there to doe, but if it be a perſon of account, the miniſter perhaps will accompany them as a priuate friend, but not as a Paſtor: In this buſines no body muſt pray, for feare of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accoumed a Papiſt. Behould Caluiniſme the ſecond bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a beard, that is without any ceremony at al, no, he renounceth al as you ſee euen at his death: and ſo let him be buried. Geneua is the chieſe ſeate of the Caluiniſts, and they are in the Palſgraue his country, but jarring in ſome pointes about their Supper. There are many of them in Fraunce, but they haue no exerciſe of their Sect in Citties and Port-townes, except in Rochell, and ſome few beſides. There they call themſelues bretheren of the Religion refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but ordinarily they be called Hugonots: There be ſome of them ſcattered in other parts of Germany, and in other countries, as alſo in great Brittaine; but there they haue no liberty, nor free exerciſe of their Religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Anabaptiſts.</head>
            <p>BAlthazar Hubincer learned the doctrine of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts firſt of Luther, and vvas burned for the ſame: He would not content himſelfe with Luther his Sect, but broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Anabaptiſme in Morauia; of the ſame faction was Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Muncer an apoſtata Prieſt, diſciple of Carolaſtade, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Starke was another; theſe drewe their doctrine out of Luther his bookes: They faigned that the Angell Gabriell appeared to them, and reuealed their Religion.</p>
            <p>Muncer cried out againſt Catholikes and Lutherans, he made ſhew to deteſt vices were they neuer ſo ſmale, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted his followers to faſtings, prayers, and to auſterities to chaſtiſe the fleſh. Menna another of the ſame Sect, called Luthers doctrine carnall, diſſolute, and more impious then the Religion of Turks and Tartars. This Muncer made ſhew of wonderfull ſimplicity, not only in his preachings but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in his cerriage, in his atire, and manner of life; he often
<pb facs="tcp:6336:16"/>faigned to be in meditation, as in an extaſie, and after tolde meruailous viſions, as though he had talked with God, his his prayer was this, lifting vp his eies towards Heauen: Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, powre into my ſoule a zealous deſire of thy juſtice, which if thou doe not I will deny thee, and al thine Apoſtles: the like did many others his companions. He taught that al were bretheren as children of a damme, and that it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon that ſome ſhould ſtarue, whileſt others ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in vvealth, and that the Apoſtles had nothing of thrir own, but al was common: This doctrine drew infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of people, and cauſed ſtraunge commotions, ſeditions, and wars. Some counterfeired miracles, and ſome ſodainely could read, which knew no letter in the booke before; who comming againe to be Catholikes, loſt their skil in reading, This Muncer afterwards was put to death, who tooke it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, and with wonderfull courage, and exhorted Princes to read the Bible, and to vnderſtand the word of God.</p>
            <p>After this mans death, they made themſelues a King, and Prophets, who tooke vpon them, to inſpire the holy Ghoſt into others; but they were after taken and ſuffered death.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> What Anbaptiſme is.</head>
            <p>THey firſt holde as all Heretiks haue done, that nothing is to be beleeued, but what is expreſly ſet downe in the Bible, and by that they proue what they will, as the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran doth, who taketh in hand to prooue by Scripture, that drunkennes pleaſeth God. In a booke printed at Lipſe, and dedicated to the Counteſſe of Mansfield, they affirme, that there is no true Church but theirs; when they will chooſe their Paſtours, they aſſemble the people, and the moſt aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſheweth the neceſſity of ſuch a flocke vnprouided: euery one giueth his voice for the election, and vpon whome the lotte falleth, he taketh an oath to gouerne and rule well the flocke. This new dignity giueth the Paſtor neither title nor
<pb facs="tcp:6336:17"/>degree, for being a craftſman, he carryeth the marks and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of his trade, and hath no ſhewe at all of a Paſtour; they haue Deacons alſo in the ſame faſhion, they haue no penſion or wages, but liue by their labors as others doe, &amp; from the pulpit they goe to the plough or cart, or to their worke, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their trade. They wil medle with no churches nor temples, but make their aſſemblies in howſes, as is to be ſeene et Fluſhing, Midleboroug, Danſieke, Camfer, Amſterdam, and in other partes of the lowe Countries. They come not where Catholiks or Lutherans doe gouerne, but are in Friſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Weſtfalia, Pruſſia, Sileſia, Morauia, in ſome parts of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, and in ſome places belonging to the King of Poland.</p>
            <p>They baptize none, vntill they come to the yeares of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and if any come to be of their Sect, who was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed when he vvas a child, they chriſten him againe, and of this they take their name. They cannot endure the Maſſe, but content themſelues with prayer and preaching, they beleeue not Purgatory, neither doe they pray to Saintes,: they haue no Images or ſigne of the Croſſe, neither doe they any reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at the name of Ieſus. They teach that no man ought to be forced for his faith, but that euery one muſt be free in ſuch thinges: They beleeue and celebrate the Supper as the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſtes doe, for the moſt parte, but theſe receiue ſtanding only, and carry it to the ſicke, but they neuer ſinge pſalme, ballad, not any ſong.</p>
            <p>When any man or woman commeth to be baptized, he preſenteth himſelfe to the aſſembly, and vpon his knees he deſireth it, and giueth teſtimony of his faith: and if he be a magiſtrate, he muſt forgoe his office. If they knewe him to be of good life, the Paſtor caſteth water vpon his head, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I baptize thee in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, without anything elſe.</p>
            <p>They outwardly ſhew great piety and zeale of Religion, and cuery one aſſureth himſelfe that he hath the holy Ghoſt, and that he doth not ſinne; and indeed in their negotiations and worldly buſineſſe, vvhat iniury ſoeuer is offered vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6336:17"/>them, you ſhall neuer ſee them paſſionate or in choller, but alwaies milde and quiet, and moſt bould and conſtant in their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>They perſwade themſelues that they ſee many viſions, and that the ſpirit reuealeth vnto them things to come: but how often haue they beene deceaued. Iohn of Lerden their firſt King, and ſecond prophet, foreſawe that he ſhould be the Emperour of the world; but he was ſoone diſpatched by the hangman. A woman priſoner at Baſill, propheſied that ſhee ſhould liue without meate, which ſhee did nine dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but dyed the tenth day. Many times they haue fore-tould the day of judgement, and haue expected it lying in the colde night vpon rockes, with a white ſheet about them, waiting for Chriſt his comming. A yonge woman amongſt them married to a Monke, being ſo poore that they had not bread to put in their mouths, ſhee had a reuelation that ſhee ſhould inuite her friendes and neighbours to a feaſte, with promiſe that nothing ſhould be wanting; ſhee did ſo, and many came inuited, all ranne after to ſee the miracle: Shee borrowed many tables, at which the gueſts were placed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting their victuals, ſhee willed them to haue patience a while, and they ſhould ſee Angels bring meate abundantly from Heauen; ſhee prayed with ſighes and ſobs euen vntill night, but nothing came, which made her gueſts in a furie halfe famiſhed, to goe home in haſte to get ſome victuals. Hoffinan their great preacher, taught them to ſuffer wrongs without murmuring, not to defend themſelues, hut to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all for the honor of God, to doe good for euill, to beare no armes, nor vſe any words, or weapon, but only prayers. They apprehend no malefactor, they will be no magiſtrates, they ſay that their Paſtors and aſſemblies ſuffice for al. They deteſt ſwearing more then any thing in the vvorld; yea, in courts or before Iudges. They can abide no Images, and when one dieth, he is carried without pompe or ceremony, and buried in the Church-yard amongſt other Sectaries.</p>
            <p>This Sect is diuided into many petite Sectes, and one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb facs="tcp:6336:18"/>another. So as if an Anabaptiſt of Sueuia, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia, come into Holland, he cannot bee admitted into their Synagogue, except he will be baptized againe. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Sects amongſt them are Apoſtoliques, which ſay that they liue as the Apoſtles did, theſe haue all their goods in common. In Morauia are many thouſands of this ſect, none hath any goods, or poſſeſſions, they til the ground for others, and haue trades, but all haue equall profit, none can bee of their Religion but ſuch as will labour, they get much and ſpend little, which cauſeth them to maintayne themſelues well.</p>
            <p>They haue ouer-ſeers, which ſee, that euery one hath what he needeth. They haue beſides ſpirituall Fathers, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in Religion, and reade the prayers in their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. Whileſt the Father readeth with a lowd voyce, houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his hands together, the reſt ſigh, ioyning their hands, but ſpeaking no word. Then they departe euery one to his worke. They haue no other preaching, nor other kinde of prayer. They celebrate their Supper twice in the yeare, and men and women ſit at it pell mell, inuiting one another to eate with great modeſty. They vſe alſo great temperance in their houſes, for ſitting downe at table, they remayne almoſt a quarter of an houre with their hands ioyned againſt their mouth, not ſpeaking a word, but doe meditate and pray by hart, whilſt they eate they haue an old Archimandrite, which marketh them without ſpeaking any word, when they haue eaten they returne in great ſilence to their labours. At worke you ſhall ſee thirty or forty together, and neuer ſpeake word one to another. In all their doings they greatly obſerue cleanlyneſſe, and ſilence. To be briefe, they liue much like vnto well ordered religious perſons.</p>
            <p>They obſerue no feaſt dayes, they haue their Bible cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taild at their pleaſure, and are very skilfull in the Text, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding it moſt commonly after the Letter, and their own braine. They will not diſpute, nor reaſon of Religion.</p>
            <p>There are other Anabaptiſts termed pure, which ſay they
<pb facs="tcp:6336:18"/>are without ſinne, and therefore put out of our Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, forgiue vs our ſinnes; and holde that Chriſtians after baptiſme cannot committe ſinne.</p>
            <p>There are beſides theſe the free anabaptiſts, which will not pay tribute, nor obey Princes: Theſe affirme marriage to be ſpirituall, and haue their woemen in common, and ſay it is the motion of Gods ſpirit. Feliciatus Capitonus recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, howe one of theſe bretheren entring into his friendes howſe, tolde him that the holy ſpirit commaunded him to lie with his wife, to which he accorded, but afterwardes ſeing his daughter faire and young, no ſaid he to the wife, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſaith I muſt lie with thy daughter; the husband returning in the morning, and finding him in bed with his daughter, how now (quoth he) is the holie ſpirit a deceauer; the ſame ſpirit commaundeth me to puniſh thee for it, &amp; preſently he ſtabbed him to death with his dagger: many ſuch tragedies haue bin ſeene amongſt them, iſſuing out of their doctrine.</p>
            <p>There be many moe diuerſities among them, which here to recount would be ouer tedious, let theſe ſuffice for this briefe treatiſe: Behould the third brother with no beard at all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Anglianiſme.</head>
            <p>SEctes of Religion are diuerſly tearmed, ſome take their names of the authors, as Arianiſme of Arius, Lutheraniſme of Luther, &amp;c. Some of the matter, as Anabaptiſme of repap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, or not baptizing infants, ſome of the country where it is, or of the people thereof, as Turciſme of the Turks, Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciſme of the Heathens, Anglianiſme of England, or of the Engliſh, who profeſſe the ſame Religion, being not preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in any country but in England, and in Lands belonging to that Crowne.</p>
            <p>Euery one knoweth, howe from the chriſtening of this people, they were ſtill of the Catholike Religion, vntil King Henry the eight his latter dayes, in which vpon diſpleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:6336:19"/>taken againſt the Pope, becauſe he would not diuorce him from his wiſe Lady Katherine, and permit him to marry La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Anne Balleine, he renounced the Pope, and called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe head of the Church in his Dominions, and ſupreame gouernour in Eecleſiaſticall cauſes. He was emboldened ſo to doe by Luthers reuolte, which was in his time, albeit Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would alow of no viſible headſhip, neither did he regard Luther nor his doctrine: He tooke vpon him this title firſt of all Kings chriſtened, yet did he not chaunge Religion but in few points, but put downe Abbeis and Religious howſes.</p>
            <p>In the dayes of his ſonne King Edward being a childe, the Kingdome vvas gouerned by his vncle the Lord prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, who to make himſelfe great put downe Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and brought in a religion compoſed by his preachers, partly of Luthers, and partly of Caluins Sect: but the childe King dying within fewe yeares, Catholike Religion was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored againe by Queene Marie, who liued not long. To her ſucceeded Ladie Elizabeth her ſiſter, who beginning her raigne in Nouember, ſuffered the Catholike Religion vntill midſomes after, becauſe they had nothing yet framed to put in place thereof, for ſhee would not allowe of her brothers Religion in all points, nor of the Bible: Shee could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Caluiniſts, nor ſhee had no liking of Luthers Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Shee deemed with a french Hugonot of Gaſcony that Caluins Religion was too leane, and the Catholike Religion too fatte, becauſe the one had many ceremonies, the other none. Shee would haue the Churches ſtill to ſtand, and the names of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Parſons, Vicars, Curates, &amp;c. Shee appointed her Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and made them by her letters Patents, and confirmed them in that calling by the authority of the Parliament. The manner of their ordering is this: The Prince nominateth them, then an Archbiſhop with two more Biſhops conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crateth them (as they tearme it) with prayers, and impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Their habit is ſomething Prieſt like, with a corner-cap and a rochet; all the clergy mengoe ordinarily in blacke, but
<pb facs="tcp:6336:19"/>the moſt part of them weare ruffes much like merchants, but not altogether ſo large: as for jerkins, dublets, breeches, and ſuch like, many of the Miniſters make them after the neweſt faſhion taken vp, as the lay men doe. They be al married ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept very few, which may marry alſo if they will; Biſhops, Deanes, Archedeacons, yet the Archbiſhop of Canterbury the Metropolitan of England liueth vnmarried, but that is voluntary and not by any bondage. Theſe Biſhoppes make Deacons and Miniſters, with impoſition of hands, and with few other ceremonies. The Biſhops haue the ſame Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riks which were in Chtholike time, and the ſame places and titles, but not ſo large reuenues. The Miniſters haue parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, vicarages, and other benefices as in olde time, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are curtaild. Theſe clergy men are bound to no offices nor prayers, more then the lay men be, but if they haue benefices or cures, they muſt reade their ſeruice in the Church, or preach vpon ſondaies and holidaies: their Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions appointe them to read ſomthing in the Church, vpon wedneſdaies, fridaies, and vpon vigils and euens, in manner of an euenſong; but that cuſtom is litle obſerued, and in few places, as alſo their holydaies grow out of vſe, and are litle regarded. They uſe churches which were in Gatholike time, but nothing is left within them but a table for the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and a pulpit or ſeate to reade prayer in: In place where the Crucifixe was behinde the high Aultar, there are the Kings armes, but no picture or image of Saint is ſeene there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, no, ſcarcely in the glaſſe windowes.</p>
            <p>They haue a forme of prayer, which they call diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, conſiſting of a kind of general confeſſion, with a kinde of inuitatory, three pſalmes, two chapters of the Bible, ſome collects, a kinde of litanies, ten commaundements, epiſtle, and goſpell, a fewe collects againe, and then the peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>But of this many make ſmale account, but all the recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is of a ſermon, and ordinarily they haue two vpon ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day: as for their ſeruice they ſay it by peeces omitting what
<pb facs="tcp:6336:20"/>they will, yea if occaſion, ſerue, before and after the ſermon they ſing a ſection of a Geneua pſalme, turned into rime in the vulgar tongue, here all ſing, boyes, wenches, woemen, and all ſorts.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter in his ſermon vpon theſe dayes, ſhould by their lawes weare a ſurpleſſe, and a corner cappe, but great ſtirres haue beene and are yet ſomtimes about this buſineſſe: Some would weare them, but their wiues will not conſent thereto, ſome for refuſing them haue loſt their benefices, and ſome haue fled away and become Caluiniſts, and ſome of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sectes, and theſe kinde of men ordinarily diſlike their ſeruice, and ceremonies</p>
            <p>They haue two ſacraments, baptiſme and the ſupper, and the Biſhops ſometimes doe confirme after a new faſhion, but account it only a ceremony, and no ſacrament, neyther doe they much vrge it. They baptize moſt commonly at the font in the Church, with ſome ceremonies taken from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, as with the ſigne of the croſſe, but that is moſt odious to the purer ſorte. By the lawes they ſhould miniſter their Communion in ſinging bread, as Catholikes vſe, but many will none of that, but vſe common loafe bread in ſteed thereof, and they haue a ſiluer cuppe wherein they giue the wine: all by the lawe muſt receiue kneeling.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter at the firſt beginning comming to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion table, muſt turne his face into the weſt, but that was after altered, and he appointed to turne to the north, which yet at the length was changed, and now he hath his face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſouth, and the weſt, when he readeth ſeruice.</p>
            <p>The Prince with the Parliament may determine of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and what by them is ſet forth muſt be obſerued.</p>
            <p>They haue beſides, many other obſeruauces taken from Catholike Religion, as in ſome Churches wearing of coaps, playing on organs, ſinging in the olde Sarum tune and ſuch like: they wed with a ring, and bury with ſolemnity the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter meeting the corps, readeth praiers and other things.</p>
            <p>Their lawes binde them to celebrate and keepe holy the
<pb facs="tcp:6336:20"/>dayes of the Apoſtles, and of many other Saintes, as alſo to faſt lent, on vigils, and to abſtaine from fleſh on fridaies and ſatterdayes, but fewe obſerue them, or faſt or abſtaine from fleſh any day, if any doe he is ſuſpected to be a Papiſt. Indeed great perſonages, and ſuch as be in high offices &amp; dignities, wil vſually haue their tables furniſhed with fiſh and ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of fleſh on ſuch dayes, and euery man may cate what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him, but if he eate no fleſh he is deemed to be no ſound Proteſtant, for ſo they tearme them of their Religion, but impropetly, for the name is proper to the Lutherans, as is ſaid, and agreeth to none other.</p>
            <p>King Iames ſince he came to the Croune, hath cauſed ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies to be moſt ſtrictly kept, and this they call the Saboath, and obſerue it almoſt as preciſely, as the Iewes doe their ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday, but of other holidayes there is litle regard.</p>
            <p>There are beſides in this land other petite Sects lurking in corners, as Brouniſts, Anabaptiſts, Family of lone, and Traſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites now beginning not heard of before, but becauſe they be obſcure &amp; not allowed of, I paſſe them ouer with ſilence.</p>
            <p>Heare maieſt thou plainly ſee that the religion of England, is compoſed of Catholike Religion, of Lutheraniſme, and Caluiniſme, and yet approueth no one of them, but differeth much from euery one, ſingled out by themſelues. Diuers ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies thou ſeeſt in this Religion, and diuers reiected, ſo that this is plainly the fourth brother with halfe a beard.</p>
            <p>Now ponder with thy ſelfe, (my gentle Reader) and then judge whether thou haſt reaſon, to leaue the Catholike and vniuerfall Church of Chriſtendome, continued throughout the world for ſo many ages together, and ſtill is flouriſhing, to joyne thy ſelfe to any one of theſe late riſen Sects; and of which ſoeuer thou art, al the reſt wil condemne thee: If thou haue but the leaſte ſparke of Gods grace to aſſiſt thee, thou wilt eaſily determine to take the beſt and ſafeſt way.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>And ſo fare thou well.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
